in this video we will show you how to
pour a basic lateral design the heart
and i believe it's the most fundamental
latte art pattern to learn so let's
start with that one the base of a nicely
poured heart is a perfectly steamed milk
if you're just starting with lottery art
and you didn't steam milk before you can
watch our previous video where we went
through milk steaming step by step today
we'll go through all the tiny hand
movements axis tilting speed and more
i'll share with you some tips that
helped me to survive all my barista
weekends when i bought hundreds of
cappuccinos flat whites and lattes as a
bonus in the end we'll share with you
how you can train latte art without
wasting milk and coffee
now that you have pulled an espresso
shot and the milk is perfectly steamed
without any large bubbles pouring has
basically two phases face number one
mixing the milk with the espresso face
number two pouring the designer it all
looks very cool and easy but it reminds
me a lot of learning how to play a
guitar all the hand positions and small
movements are easier to do when you
train them separately and in slow motion
that would be a key advice if you're
just starting with the latte art the
slower the training the stronger is
getting the so-called muscle memory try
to be very conscious of what you do
how you hold things and how you pour
phase one mixing the milk with the
espresso
as lance hendrick from onyxcoffee said
think of the espresso base as of a
canvas you want to stretch the canvas
all over the cup so the paint can hold
on it by mixing the espresso with a drop
of milk we create a much more stable
surface for the latter design we're
filling up approximately one third to a
half of the cup with milk and mixing it
all together we're doing so because the
espresso behaves like an oil liquid if
we just pour straight on top of the
espresso the milk pattern won't hold its
shape and the design would lack contrast
very important when we pour we need to
hit the espresso hard so the milk
touches the bottom of the cup goes back
to the surface and mixes with the crema
all around
this is how to do it hold the cup in
your less dominant hand
you can hold it in your palm like this
or you can preferably hold it by the
handle the handle should be right in
front of your chest pointing to you
this way you make sure that the final
design is perfectly symmetric and when
you put it on the table it faces the
customer now we're gonna tilt the cup
with the espresso by 30 to 40 degrees
towards the spout you want to see the
liquids almost touching the edge of the
cup as you can see the espresso now sits
both between the wall and on the bottom
of the cup we create more depth in the
liquid which is very important for the
first pour now we're gonna take the
pitcher with the milk grab the pitcher
by your dominant hand
you can grab the picture like this you
can grab it at the bottom
or you can grab it by the handle it
doesn't matter find your way in a
position where you feel in control you
want to be able to steadily control the
flow of the milk
hold the pitcher
tilt the cup towards the spout
twist the wrist with the pitcher and
pour rather aggressively along the
vertical axis straight to the point
where the cup is tilted
move from side to side all around the
cup that helps you to mix the milk with
the espresso properly fill approximately
half of the cup by pouring along the
vertical axis turn the cup back into the
horizontal position and swirl with the
milk and espresso we're doing that to
get rid of the color of the crema which
disrupts the contrast of the design
you can also use spoon to mix the coffee
with the milk if you struggle with the
hand movement i still like to use the
spoon as it is very effective when you
get good at swelling motion you can
start doing it simultaneously while
pouring but that is more advanced now
we've stretched the canvas and we're
ready to paint in phase two we're
literally almost touching the surface of
the coffee with the spout
bottom of the picture goes up and all
around phase two the pitcher is touching
the rim of the cup very important the
tip of the spout is in the middle of the
cup the whole time
following the vertical axis as it
defaults glued to it now we need to
paint the design on our canvas to do
that we're adding a new motion and that
is wiggling
you can do it with your elbow like this
or you can do it with your wrist
being loose like this a small chip for
wiggling
when you train the motion with just the
water and the cup soon you'll get the
feeling into your hands
ice on the tip of the spout
the spout is inside the cup nearly
touching the coffee
now start wiggling with the jug from
left to right
stay at the vertical axis stay in the
middle of the cup make sure you don't
travel with a pitcher as you're filling
up the cup start tilting the cup back to
its horizontal position take your time
make your life easier there is no need
to rush this part the cup is full
raise the pitcher up and cut through
make sure you rise up at least 10
centimeters
a common mistake is cutting through the
design too low
where the stream is too thick and it
destroys the pattern
you need a thin stream of milk and for
that you need height again
let's show it again with milk and in
slow motion swill with the jug destroy
all visible bubbles
tilt the cup towards the spout 30 to 40
degrees
phase one
pour quickly under the espresso along
the vertical axis start
and finish in the center
fill the cup to the half
mix the base canvas is ready phase two
go down with the spout lower edge
touching the cup tip of the spout almost
touching the coffee
stay at the axis
wiggle from left to right maintain the
same speed do not rush
level the cup to horizontal position as
it's getting full
stay in the middle
the cup is full
raise the pitcher about 15 centimeters
up cut the design in half
the heart is done
result unified texture no visible
bubbles symmetric design shiny surface a
high contrast no blurry parts taste wise
delicious
bonus round i didn't want to scare you
in the beginning of the video but it
takes a while before being able to pour
a design like that the purpose of this
video was sharing a shortcut with you to
a great result now just two more tips
for the training itself instead of using
milk fill the pitcher with cold water
and add a drop of detergent steam it as
you would steam the milk
instead of a shot of espresso you can
use diluted cacao powder which is much
cheaper the result might be more bubbly
or not perfect don't worry about that
these tips are here to help you with
your movements and muscle memory and to
eliminate waste
what do you think did you find this
video helpful did you find something
that doesn't work for you perhaps you
have some tips on how to pour latte out
too
let us know in the comments in the next
video we will look at pouring specific
latter designs like rosetta or a tulip
have a great day and i'll see you in the
next video
[Music]